<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<article xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0"
	 xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
	 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
	 xml:id="nscreen-protocol" xml:lang="en" class="specification">
  <info>

    <title>nScreen Protocol Specification</title>
	<subtitle>Version 1.0</subtitle>

	<orgname>Intel Corporation</orgname>

    <author>
      <personname>
	<firstname>Tomas</firstname> <surname>Frydrych</surname>
<!--
      <affiliation>
        <orgname>Intel Corporation</orgname>
      </affiliation>
-->
      </personname>
      <email>tf@linux.intel.com</email>
    </author>

    <revhistory>
      <revision>
         <revnumber>0.1</revnumber>
         <date>22 October 2010</date>
         <revremark>Initial draft</revremark>
      </revision>
      <revision>
         <revnumber>0.2</revnumber>
         <date>22 October 2010</date>
         <revremark>...</revremark>
      </revision>
    </revhistory>
  </info>

<?hard-pagebreak?>

  <section xml:id="intro">
    <title>Introduction</title>
    <para>
      Users often carry out similar activities on different devices, e.g., watch
      videos on a smart phone, laptop, or a TV set. However, as the user moves
      in time and space, the optimal choice of a device for any given activity
      might change: a smart phone might be the optimal video viewing platform
      while travelling on a train, but a TV set might be optimal in the comfort
      of one's living room.
    </para>

    <para>
      The nScreen framework aims to facilitates seamless transition of the
      user's activities as she moves around. It does so by providing a
      communication channels through which individual user-facing applications
      on distinct devices can cooperate and coordinate their discrete
      behaviours, and in so construct a dynamic and homogeneous experience
      spanning the devices involved.
    </para>

    <para>
      The activities for which consumers use computers are impossible to
      enumerate, and are set to evolve. Consequently the nScreen framework does
      not seek to narrowly define the activities and/or services that might fall
      withing its scope, nor it seeks to prescribe the ways in which such
      activities or tasks should be accomplished. Rather the nScreen framework
      is a set of generic protocols that can support new activities and services
      without the need to modify the core protocols.
    </para>

    <para>
      More specifically, the aims of the nScreen framework are as follows:
    </para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  To provide unified discovery, connection and transport mechanism that
	  could be utilised on a variety of hardware and software platforms by a
	  wide spectrum of user-facing applications,
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  To provide means for transmitting meta-data describing user-oriented
	  activities, and doing so in secure manner protecting user privacy,
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  To provide standard meta-data definitions for most common user-facing
	  activities, so as to allow common classes of applications to
	  inter-operate without having to know anything about the implementation
	  details of their nScreen partners.
	</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <section xml:id="intro-usecases">
      <title>Basic Use cases</title>

      <para>
	nScreen use cases fall into two broad categories:
      </para>

      <para>
	<itemizedlist>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Subscription-based services: these are provided by discrete
	      entities, each operating their own nScreen server. nScreen users
	      connect to this server using credentials agreed with the service
	      provider, and interact with applications provided by the service
	      provider through their server.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Applications interacting within a home cloud: the home cloud use
	      case differs from the subscription service by the absence of a
	      central server; instead the cloud transparently fulfils the role
	      of a subscription-less server.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
      </para>

      <para>
	The nScreen framework aims to support both of these scenarios in a
	transparent manner.
      </para>

    </section>

    <section xml:id="intro-mesh">
      <title>The nScreen Mesh</title>
	  <para>
	    Structurally, the nScreen mesh consists of for tiers, as per the
	    following figure:

	    <annotation role="todo">
	      <info>
		<authorinitials>tf</authorinitials>
	      </info>
	      <para>
		Diagram
	      </para>
	    </annotation>
	  </para>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="intro-application-classes">
      <title>Application Classes</title>

      <para>
	nScreen applications can be divided into two broad classes:

	<itemizedlist>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Task-oriented applications: these are the principal participants
	      in the nScreen mesh. They are user-facing applications such as
	      media players, that have been enriched by adding the nScreen
	      capabilities.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Control Applications: these provide background nScreen services on
	      an nScreen-enabled devices. their principal purpose is to allow
	      task-oriented applications to direct their communications at a
	      device, rather than a specific task-oriented application on that
	      device, and to ensure that appropriate task-oriented application
	      is available (e.g., by spawning of suitable application on the
	      device in response to incoming requests).
	    </para>

	    <para>
	      While control applications can be purely background processes,
	      when provided with a suitable UI they can be used as generic
	      nScreen remote controls.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
      </para>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="intro-document-structure">
      <title>Document Structure</title>

      <para>
	The remainder of this document is divided into three parts: <xref
	linkend="comm-protocols"/>, describes the protocols that define the
	nScreen communication backbone, <xref linkend="local-nscreen"/>,
	specifies link-local nScreen protocol used for server-less nScreen
	communication, and <xref linkend="messaging"/>, describes the nScreen
	messaging protocols and metadata model.
      </para>
    </section>
  </section>

<?hard-pagebreak?>

  <section xml:id="comm-protocols">
    <title>Communication Backbone Protocols</title>

    <section xml:id="comm-protocols-intro">
      <title>Overview</title>

      <para>
	The nScreen communication protocols are built on the existing XMPP (aka
	'jabber') standard. The reasons for choosing XMPP as the basic transport
	protocol are:

	<itemizedlist>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Using an established standard means that much of the wheel needs
	      not to be reinvented,
	    </para>
	  </listitem>

	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      XMPP is supported on a broad range of hardware and software
	      platforms, thus aiding the speed with which the nScreen framework
	      can be rolled out,
	    </para>
	  </listitem>

	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      XMPP is an open standard that can be used without difficulties
	      over licensing,
	    </para>
	  </listitem>

	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      XMPP is extensible by design,
	    </para>
	  </listitem>

	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      XMPP is capable of operating both in a server-based and
	      server-less manner, and supports both of these modes a in
	      transparent way,
	    </para>
	  </listitem>


	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      XMPP is XML-based, so that implementation of extensions is
	      simplified by being able to use standard XML-processing tools,
	      such a parsers, etc.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
      </para>

      <para>
	The nScreen framework defines three sets of extensions to XMPP:

	<itemizedlist>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Enhanced subscription mechanism,
	    </para>
	  </listitem>

	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Protocols for encoding of nScreen meta-data,
	    </para>
	  </listitem>

	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      A server-less protocol similar to link-local XMPP<citation><xref
	      linkend="xep0174"/></citation> , but reserved for nScreen use.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
      </para>

      <para>
	In addition, at number of points, the nScreen specification mandates
	the use of standard, but optional, XMPP features, particularly so, where
	this is desirable to improve security and privacy.
      </para>

      <section xml:id="comm-protocols-security">
	<title>Security and Privacy Considerations</title>

	<para>
	  The flexible and extensible nature of the nScreen framework means that
	  it is not possible to predict what kind of data my be transmitted via
	  the protocol in its real-world deployment. Furthermore, the
	  expectation of deployment on variety of platforms, ranging from
	  desktop computers to mobile phones, means that multiple
	  implementations of the protocol will be in use. It is, therefore,
	  paramount that security and privacy of user data is a key factor in
	  the design of the protocol itself. More specifically:

	  <itemizedlist>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
		The protocol must facilitate privacy of data in transit,
	      </para>
	    </listitem>

	    <listitem>
	      <para>
		Reliable identity verification mechanism must be available,
	      </para>
	    </listitem>

	    <listitem>
	      <para>
		The protocol must provide structured access control to user's
		local resources.
	      </para>
	    </listitem>
	  </itemizedlist>
	</para>

	<para>
	  With regards to the above, the following should be noted:

	  <itemizedlist>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
		XMPP on its on only provides client-to-server privacy, and as
		such is susceptible to server eavesdropping,
	      </para>
	    </listitem>

	    <listitem>
	      <para>
		Normal XMPP presence information is broadcast across all
		subscribed contacts, which might not be appropriate for certain
		types of data that might be included in nScreen extended status
		message.
	      </para>
	    </listitem>
	  </itemizedlist>
	</para>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="comm-protocols-sub-and-authentication">
      <title>nScreen Subscription and Authentication</title>

      <section xml:id="comm-protocols-authentication">
	<title>Authentication</title>

	<para>
	  Authentication is accomplished via SASL per core XMPP
	  protocol<citation><xref linkend="rfc3920"/></citation>. SASL
	  authentication must be implemented both for both server-based and
	  server-less contexts.
	</para>
      </section>

      <section xml:id="comm-protocols-identity">
	<title xml:id="comm-protocols-identity-title">
	Identity Verification
	</title>

	<section xml:id="comm-protocols-identity-server">
	  <title>Identity Verification in Server-Based Context</title>

	  <para>
	    Standard XMPP does not provide a formal mechanism for identity
	    verification. Because the authentication of two communicating users
	    A and B is typically done separately and independently by two
	    different servers, A's trust in B's identity implies A's trust in
	    the authentication procedures of B's service provider, which cannot
	    be automatically granted.  Therefore, this generic scenario is only
	    acceptable if data exchanged between A and B contains no sensitive
	    information, i.e., for what essentially amounts to an anonymous
	    nScreen service.
	  </para>

	  <para>
	    An nScreen service that requires reliable identity verification must
	    be implemented using a dedicated nScreen server that requires direct
	    login, and does not permit server hops (i.e., both A and B are
	    logging into the same server in order to talk to each other). In
	    this situation the service provider is fully in control of the
	    authentication procedure, and, assuming 1:1 mapping between users
	    and their authentication credentials is in place, successful
	    authentication provides also identity verification.
	</para>
	</section>

	<section xml:id="comm-protocols-identity-cloud">
	  <title>Identity Verification in Server-Less Context</title>

	  <para>
	    In server-less context of a home cloud, the 1:1 mapping between
	    nScreen users and authentication credentials cannot be guaranteed; a
	    simple home cloud set up might rely on a shared secret to allow
	    applications across the cloud to authenticate, which in turn allows
	    an authenticated application to spoof another application.
	  </para>

	  <para>
	    Although identity spoofing carries with it lesser risks in the
	    context of the home cloud, the following messures are required to be
	    taken by compliant nScreen implementations to improve security:

	    <itemizedlist>
	      <listitem>
		<para>
		  Applications must not make assumptions about identity of other
		  nScreen participants in the cloud context, unless they
		  implement additional identity verification procedures not
		  specifiend by the current version of the nScreen protocol,
		</para>
	      </listitem>

	      <listitem>
		<para>
		  Applications running both in server-based and server-less
		  contexts must not inject data from server-based streams into
		  the cloud.
		</para>
	      </listitem>
	    </itemizedlist>
	  </para>
	</section>

	<section xml:id="comm-protocols-identity-future">
	  <title>Future Expectations</title>

	  <para>
	    Additional identity verification mechanism addressing the current
	    limitations, using more robust mechanisms (such as PKI) will be
	    defined in future versions of the protocol.
	  </para>
	</section>
      </section>

      <section xml:id="comm-protocols-subscription">
	<title>Subscription</title>

	<para>
	  The nScreen framework, requires subscription mechanism that will (a)
	  work both for server-driven and server-less connections, and (b)
	  ensure that the end-user, rather than the server owner, maintains
	  access control to their own local resources. Since standard XMPP
	  provides only a server-centric subscription mechanism; this
	  specification defines an additional, local, subscription, protocol.
	</para>

	<para>
	  The extended subscription protocol, described further on, is closely
	  tied to a format of application JID, which is described first.
	</para>

	<section xml:id="comm-protocols-jid">
	  <title>nScreen JID form</title>

	  <para>
	    A fully qualified JID (jabber id) identifies a single participant in
	    the nScreen mesh. As in standard XMPP, a fully qualified JID
	    consists of a bare JID and a resource identifier; the bare JID
	    identifies a user, while a fully qualified JID identifies a single
	    connection by that user to the nScreen mesh (multiple simultaneous
	    connections by single bare JID are allowed for obvious reasons). An
	    example of a bare JID would be 'someone@somewhere.com' while a fully
	    qualified JID would be 'someone@somewhere.com/myresource'
	  </para>

	  <para>
	    In the remainder of this document, the term 'JID' is used to refer
	    to bare JIDs; if a fully qualified jabber id is meant, this will
	    always be explicitly stated.
	  </para>

	  <para>
	    nScreen JIDs fall into three broad categories: JIDs for outward
	    (customer) facing services offered by service providers, inward
	    facing JIDs used to identify customers to service providers, and
	    JIDs used for server-less connections in a home cloud.
	  </para>

	  <section xml:id="comm-protocols-jid-outward">
	    <title>Outward-facing JIDs</title>

	    <para>
	      <itemizedlist>
		<listitem>
		  <para>
		    The canonical form of an outward-facing JID is
		    'application.subdomain.domain@service-provider', and
		    reflects the notional structuring of the nScreen mesh. This
		    form of JID must be used for all outward facing connections.
		  </para>
		</listitem>

		<listitem>
		  <para>
		    The principal reason for this structuring is to facilitate a
		    uniform feel for customer facing UIs regardless of
		    application or service provider: client side implementations
		    of the nScreen specification are expected to organise their
		    connection rosters using this 4 tier scheme.
		  </para>
		</listitem>

		<listitem>
		  <para>
		    As with normal XMPP JIDs, the service-provider part of the
		    JID (the part after the @ symbol) must be an Internet domain
		    name that can be resolved through a DNS service,
		  </para>
		</listitem>

		<listitem>
		  <para>
		    Service providers are free do define the domains and
		    sub-domains in a way that fulfils their specific needs, for
		    example, an 'easymart.com' provider could define per-store
		    domains and per-department sub-domains:
		  </para>

		  <para>
		    .menswear.broadway-store@easymart.com
		  </para>
		</listitem>

		<listitem>
		  <para>
		    The leftmost part of the JID must identify the individual
		    application that is providing the service in question,
		  </para>
		</listitem>

		<listitem>
		  <para>
		    Multiple connection by single application are differentiated
		    by the resource id of the fully qualified JID.
		  </para>
		</listitem>
	      </itemizedlist>
	    </para>
	  </section>

	  <section xml:id="comm-protocols-jid-inward">
	    <title>Inward-facing JIDs</title>

	    <para>
	      Inward facing JIDs are used to identify customer connections to a
	      service provider; no special restrictions beyond those specified
	      by the core XMPP protocol are placed on these by the nScreen
	      specification.
	    </para>
	  </section>


	  <section xml:id="comm-protocols-jid-serverless">
	    <title>Server-less JIDs</title>

	    <para>
	      <itemizedlist>
		<listitem>
		  <para>
		    Server-less JIDs are used for server-less connections inside
		    home cloud (i.e., running over the local-nscreen protocol
		    specified later in this document).
		  </para>
		</listitem>

		<listitem>
		  <para>
		    Server-less JIDs are outward-facing JIDs without the
		    service-provider part, i.e., they have the form
		    'application.device.domain'.
		  </para>
		</listitem>

		<listitem>
		  <para>
		    The device part of the JID should be obtained automatically
		    using a suitable mechanism (such as the host name); this is
		    to ensure that all applications running on the same physical
		    device use the same 'device' id.
		  </para>
		</listitem>

		<listitem>
		  <para>
		    The domain part of the JID should identify the home
		    cloud. (Though the present version of the specification does
		    not provide for server-less connections that cross the cloud
		    boundary, such mechanism might be added in future versions.)
		  </para>
		</listitem>

		<listitem>
		  <para>
		    Multiple connections by the same application are
		    differentiated by the resource id.
		  </para>
		</listitem>
	      </itemizedlist>
	    </para>
	  </section>
	</section>

	<section xml:id="comm-protocols-server-subscription">
	  <title>Server-end subscription</title>

	  <para>
	    nScreen subscription services operated through an nScreen XMPP
	    server are built around normal XMPP subscription mechanisms as
	    specified by the core XMPP protocol <citation><xref
	    linkend="rfc3920"/></citation>, and nScreen servers should comply
	    with the subscription policies this specification sets out.
	  </para>

	  <para>
	    Available outward facing application should be advertised by the
	    server via XMPP pubsub mechanism <citation><xref
	    linkend="xep0060"/></citation>.
	  </para>
	</section>

	<section xml:id="comm-protocols-local-subscrition">
	  <title>Local Subscription</title>

	  <annotation role="comment">
	    <info>
	      <authorinitials>tf</authorinitials>
	    </info>
	    <para>
	      I suspect this is the biggest departure from the normal workings
	      of XMPP.
	    </para>
	  </annotation>

	  <para>
	    Server-end subscription cannot be relied upon to provide adequate
	    access control to resources owned by a given user, since the
	    enforcement of the subscription policies is controlled by the
	    service provider, not the user; in order to avoid situations such as
	    users' rosters flooded by unwanted applications that they do not
	    wish to interact with (even if from well-meaning vendors),
	    additional local subscription mechanism is used to control incoming
	    traffic.
	  </para>

	  <para>
	    Similarly, there is a need for access control mechanism when
	    operating within a server-less cloud, so as to avoid equating
	    connection to the cloud with blank access to all nScreen
	    services. This local subscription mechanism facilitates such finer
	    grained access control in server-less setup.
	  </para>

	  <para>
	    The local subscriptions only control incoming traffic, and
	    consequently there are only three subscription states:

	    <itemizedlist>
	      <listitem>
		<para>
		 'Yes'  : communication enabled,
		</para>
	      </listitem>

	      <listitem>
		<para>
		  'No' : remote client barred from communicating with local
		  client,
		</para>
	      </listitem>

	      <listitem>
		<para>
		  'Unset': initial value
		</para>
	      </listitem>
	    </itemizedlist>
	  </para>

	  <para>
	    The meaning of the 'Unset' value is controlled by local policy; the
	    user might choose 'Unset' to mean 'No', or she might choose 'Unset'
	    to mean 'allow remote initiation of new subscriptions'.
	  </para>

	  <para>
	  The local subscription mechanism facilitates not only per-application
	  subscriptions, but also subscriptions per sub-domain, domain and
	  service-provider, i.e., the user can subscribe to (or block) all
	  applications by particular service provider, or all applications in a
	  particular domain of a specific service provider.
	  </para>

	  <para>
	    The subscription database is queried from more complete
	    subscriptions toward broader subscription classes. An example
	    subscription database for online store application on a phone of a
	    specific user could look like:
	  </para>

	  <programlisting>
        mens-wear.easymart.com      | Yes
        ties.mens-wear@easymart.com | No
	  </programlisting>

	  <para>
	    Meaning, the local user is happy to interact with applications in
	    the mens-wear domain of easymart.com, except applications in the
	    ties sub-domain. Depending on the local policy, the user might
	    either want all subscriptions requests from easymart.com rejected
	    (implicit 'No') or presented for examination.
	  </para>

	  <section xml:id="comm-protocols-local-subscription-algorithm">
	    <title>Local subscription algorithm</title>

	    <para>
	      In the following P is an nScreen application on a user end device
	      (e.g., a mobile phone), M is an external shop checkout
	      application, provided by easymart.com, with JID
	      'checkoutapp.checkout1.old-inns-service-station@easymart.com'.
	      When M is offered for addition into the roster of P by the
	      connection manager, the following subscription check is carried
	      out before user is made aware of M:
	    </para>

	    <para>

	      <orderedlist numeration="arabic">
		<listitem>
		  <para>
		    Subscription check

		    <orderedlist numeration="upperalpha">
		      <listitem>
			<para>
			  P checks subscription database for M's complete (but bare) JID:
			  <itemizedlist>
			    <listitem>
			      <para>
				Yes: P proceeds to <xref
				linkend="comm-protocols-local-subscription-algorithm-id"/>,
			      </para>
			    </listitem>
			    <listitem>
			      <para>
				No: P removes M from roster and ignores any
				further messages from M,
			      </para>
			    </listitem>

			    <listitem>
			      <para>
				Unset: P proceeds to next step,
			      </para>
			    </listitem>
			  </itemizedlist>
			</para>
		      </listitem>

		      <listitem>
			<para>
			  P continues to check the subscription database for
			  partial JIDs by removing progressively more JID
			  elements (e.g.,
			  checkout1.old-inns-service-station@easymart.com,
			  old-inns-service-station@easymart.com, easymart.com)
			  using the algorithm described in (A) until the final
			  test on service-provider:

			  <itemizedlist>
			    <listitem>
			      <para>
				Yes: P proceeds to <xref
				linkend="comm-protocols-local-subscription-algorithm-id"/>,
			      </para>
			    </listitem>

			    <listitem>
			      <para>
				No: P removes M from roster and ignores any
				further messages from M,
			      </para>
			    </listitem>

			    <listitem>
			      <para>
				Unset: P checks whether local policy allows
				automatic subscription initiation:

				<itemizedlist>
				  <listitem>
				    <para>
				      Yes: proceeds to <xref
				      linkend="comm-protocols-local-subscription-algorithm-new"/>,
				    </para>
				  </listitem>
				  <listitem>
				    <para>
				      No : P removes M from roster and stops
				      processing; any further advances by M will
				      be silently ignored.
				    </para>
				  </listitem>
				</itemizedlist>
			      </para>
			    </listitem>
			  </itemizedlist>
			</para>
		      </listitem>
		    </orderedlist>
		  </para>
		</listitem>

		<listitem xml:id="comm-protocols-local-subscription-algorithm-id">
		  <para>
		    Identity verification: See <xref
		    linkend="comm-protocols-identity"/>
		  </para>
		</listitem>

		<listitem xml:id="comm-protocols-local-subscription-algorithm-new">
		  <para>
		    New subscription

		    <orderedlist numeration="upperalpha">
		      <listitem>
			<para>
			  P asks user if she wishes to allow M to cooperate with
			  P

			  <itemizedlist>
			    <listitem>
			      <para>
				No : P sets the P 2 M subscription in local
				database to 'No' P removes M from P's roster and
				stops processing,
			      </para>
			    </listitem>
			    <listitem>
			      <para>
				Yes: P proceeds to <xref
				linkend="comm-protocols-local-subscription-algorithm-id"/>,
			      </para>
			    </listitem>
			  </itemizedlist>
			</para>
		      </listitem>
		    </orderedlist>
		  </para>
		</listitem>
	      </orderedlist>
	    </para>
	  </section>
	</section>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="comm-protocols-privacy">
      <title>Privacy Protocols</title>

      <para>
	The nScreen protocol specifies two sets of features aiming to ensure
	privacy of user data: the use of TLS and the use of end-to-end
	encryption. TLS layer facilitates private client-to-server and
	server-to-server data exchange. It does not, however, prevent
	eavesdropping by a server involved in data transmission. As such, TLS
	provides sufficient protection only for low risk data. Services wishing
	to transmit high risk data (e.g., banking details and such) must
	either secure the server (i.e., ensure no server hops are involved and
	no sensitive data is leaked in the presence information), or,
	preferably make use of end-to-end encryption in addition to TLS.
      </para>

      <section xml:id="comm-protocols-privacy-tls">
	<title>TLS</title>

	<para>
	  Compliant nScreen applications, both servers and clients, must
	  support TLS as specified by the core XMPP protocol <citation><xref
	  linkend="rfc3920"/></citation>, and must use TLS secured
	  connections exclusively, both for client-to-server and
	  server-to-server connections; both compliant servers and clients are
	  required to refuse connections that do not use TLS.
	</para>
      </section>

      <section xml:id="comm-protocols-privacy-e2e">
	<title>End to end encryption</title>

	<para>
	  The end-to-end encryption to be used by nScreen clients is described
	  by the XMPP e2e extension <citation><xref
	  linkend="rfc3923"/></citation>.

	  <annotation role="comment">
	    <info>
	      <authorinitials>tf</authorinitials>
	    </info>
	    <para>
	      Ideally, some form of e2e TLS channel for exchange of presence
	      and messages would be preferable, but the xep-e2e will do in
	      principle; we are unlikely to be implementing this initially
	      anyway.
	    </para>
	  </annotation>

	</para>
      </section>
    </section>
  </section>

  <?hard-pagebreak?>
  <section xml:id="local-nscreen">
      <title>Local-nscreen protocol</title>

      <para>
	The local-nscreen protocol allows for automatic connection between
	nScreen clients running on the same LAN. It is derived from the
	local-xmpp protocol, but with some important changes:

	<annotation role="comment">
	  <info>
	    <authorinitials>tf</authorinitials>
	  </info>
	  <para>
	    I think it should be possible to implement these difference as an
	    --nscreen command line option to salut, really.
	  </para>
	</annotation>

	<itemizedlist>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      The link-local service is called 'nscreen' rather than 'presence',
	      i.e., the PTRs have pattern 'JID._nscreen._tcp._local.',
	    </para>
	  </listitem>

	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Connection is done by JID and resource as with regular XMPP, the
	      machine part (after @) is worked out automatically,
	    </para>
	  </listitem>

	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      The TXT record contains an extra entry 'nstat' that holds the
	      <code>&lt;nscreen:status&gt;</code> output as a single line.

	      <annotation role="todo">
		<info>
		  <authorinitials>tf</authorinitials>
		</info>
		<para>
		  this has to be suitably encoded to ensure we comply with the
		  DNS-SD size limits -- for the whole TXT record 200 is
		  recommended maximum, 400 is acceptable, and 1300 is the
		  absolute maximum allowed); we should aim here not to exceed
		  the 400 limit
		</para>
	      </annotation>

	    </para>
	  </listitem>

	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      All implementations must support SASL authentication.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
      </para>
  </section>

  <?hard-pagebreak?>
  <section xml:id="messaging">
    <title>Messaging Protocols</title>

    <annotation role="comment">
      <info>
	<authorinitials>tf</authorinitials>
      </info>
      <para>
	This is the upper layer of the nScreen protocols; this is the one bit we
	have a fairly good idea what we want to do -- we already have a working
	proof-of-concept implementation of libnscreen on the top of telepathy
	working along these lines; except we do not use XML for the messages but
	use specially crafted strings inside normal presence and IM messages.
      </para>
    </annotation>

    <para>
      The purpose of the nScreen protocols is to allow applications to exchange
      meta-data that would allow them to coordinate their activity across
      multiple devices; the protocol does not aim to provide mechanisms for
      actual data transfers, though in some common and specific cases it
      mandates which other standard protocols should be used, see <xref
      linkend="messaging-data-transfer"/>.
    </para>

    <para>
      The messaging consists of three basic building blocks: application
      description information, extended status information, and instruction
      messages. Message of one the latter two types is conceptually a data tuple
      describing an activity in terms of a subject (capability in use), verb
      (the activity itself) and set of attributes (what and how). The primary
      difference between the two types of messages is in the tense: status
      message describe a present state, while instruction messages refer to a
      desired future state.
    </para>

    <para>
      In order to facilitate communication between common application classes,
      the protocol defines the subjects, verbs and attributes for common user
      activities. At the same time, new subjects, verbs and attributes can be
      defined and used by specialised applications.
    </para>

    <para>
      (For full XML definition see <xref linkend="appendix-dtd"/>.)
    </para>

    <section xml:id="messaging-app-info">
      <title>Descriptive Application Information</title>

<annotation role='todo'>
  <info>
    <authorinitials>tf</authorinitials>
  </info>
  <para>
    Rework this using xep-0030.
  </para>
</annotation>
      <para>
	nScreen applications need to provide localised descriptive information
	about themselves that can be presented to the user. Specifically, they
	have to provide localised, user-formated, strings corresponding to the
	application, sub-domain, domain and service provider components of the
	nScreen JID.
      </para>

      <para>
	In regular XMPP similar functionality is accomplished using the vCard
	mechanism<citation><xref linkend="xep0054"/></citation>. This is not
	suitable for nScreen use, firstly because the vCard specification is a
	poor fit as it was designed to describe humans, and secondly, because
	the vCard information is transmitted through the XMPP presence
	mechanism, which in the server-less context suffers from size
	constraints that make it impossible to handle fully localised vCard
	information.
      </para>

      <para>
	To address this, the nScreen specification sets out a mechanism that
	allows one application to request localised descriptive information from
	another, using XMPP iq mechanism:

	<itemizedlist>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      In order to obtain descriptive information about application B,
	      application A dispatches <code>&lt;iq</code> stanza of type 'get'
	      with xmlns attribute 'nscreen::appinfo' and xml:lang attribute
	      indicating the required locale,
	    </para>
	  </listitem>

	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Application B responds with <code>&lt;iq</code> stanza of type
	      'result', xmlns attribute 'nscreen::appinfo', holding elements
	      <code>&lt;nscreen:app-name</code>,
	      <code>&lt;nscreen:app-subdomain</code>,
	      <code>&lt;nscreen:app-domain</code>, and
	      <code>&lt;nscreen:app-provider</code> holding the localised
	      strings. Each of these elements must have the xml:lang attribute
	      set to the actual language of it's content (which might, or might
	      not match the xml:lang of the request).
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
      </para>

      <para>
	(For full description of the XML elements, see <xref
	linkend="appendix-dtd"/>).
      </para>

      <section xml:id="messaging-app-info-example">
	<title>Application Information XML example</title>

	<programlisting language="xml">
	  <![CDATA[
<iq to="colormaker.colorsforall.shop@paint.com/resource"
    type="get"
    id="appinfo1"
    xmlns="nscreen::appinfo"
    xml:lang="en-GB"/>

 ...

<iq to="a.customer@paint.com/resource"
    type="result"
    id="appinfo1"
    xmlns="nscreen::appinfo"
    xml:lang="en-GB">

  <nscreen:app-name xml:lang="en-GB">
    Colour Maker
  </nscreen:app-name>

  <nscreen:app-subdomain xml:lang="en-GB">
    Colours for All
  </nscreen:app-subdomain>

  <nscreen:app-domain xml:lang="en-GB">
    Colour Shop
  </nscreen:app-domain>

  <nscreen:app-provider xml:lang="en-US">
    Paint Inc.
  </nscreen:app-provider>
</iq>]]>
	</programlisting>

	<para>
	  Note that in the above example, the final string was not available in
	  the en-GB locale, and a fallback string in en-US locale is supplied
	  instead.
	</para>
      </section>

    </section>

    <section xml:id="messaging-status">
      <title>Extended Status</title>

      <para>
	Extended status information is encapsulated in
	<code>&lt;nscreen:status</code> element embedded inside XMPP
	<code>&lt;presence</code> stanza. The status element holds an
	unspecified number of <code>&lt;nscreen:capability</code> elements that
	describe status for each capability the client supports.

	<annotation role="comment">
	  <info>
	    <authorinitials>tf</authorinitials>
	  </info>
	  <para>
	    TP API will be needed to access this; does not have to be too
	    complex, even being able to retrieve the
	    <code>&lt;nscreen:status</code> xml snipped for local processing
	    would be sufficient, e.g., something like GetPresenceStanzaPart
	    (const char *name) that would be called as GetPresenceStanzaPart
	    ("nscreen:status").
	  </para>
	</annotation>
      </para>

      <para>
	The <code>&lt;nscreen:capability</code> element can be extended with
	custom attributes; however, no frequently changing information (such as
	current playback position) is permitted as part of status to avoid
	flooding of the network.
      </para>

      <para>
	In addition to the extended status mechanism described above, it is
	recommended that all nScreen implementations support the XMPP User
	Avatar specification<citation><xref linkend="xep0084"/></citation>.
      </para>

      <section xml:id="messaging-status-example">
	<title>Status XML example</title>

	<programlisting><![CDATA[
<nscreen:status version='1.0'
                primary-capability='ns-caps-video'>

  <nscreen:capability type='ns-caps-video'
                      activity='ns-activity-play'
                      uri='some random youtube url'
                      volume='0.75'>

    [Description]

  </nscreen:capability>
</nscreen:status>]]>
	</programlisting>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="messaging-commands">
      <title>Instruction Messages</title>

      <para>
	Instruction messages are used to send nScreen commands. The protocol
	defines a set of generic xml elements that are used to encapsulate
	nScreen messages, with parameters transmitted via xml attributes.
      </para>

      <section xml:id="messaging-commands-transport">
	<title>Message Transport</title>

	<annotation role="todo">
	  <info>
	    <authorinitials>tf</authorinitials>
	  </info>
	  <para>
	  The are multiple options here, including: (a) use <code>&lt;iq</code>
	  stanzas with suitable nScreen name-space; (b) insert
	  <code>&lt;nscreen:message</code> into <code>&lt;message</code> stanza
	  on the same level as <code>&lt;body</code>; (c) use XMPP ad-hoc
	  commands<citation><xref linkend="xep0050"/></citation>, (NB:
	  jabber-rpc is not suitable, because the RPC arguments for each call
	  are fixed in number and position.)
	</para>

	<para>
	  (a) is probably the least efficient way of doing this, I can see no
	  obvious advantages, and would need a whole API/interface for these
	  IQs.
	</para>

	<para>
	  (b) would really just need API to retrieve the
	  <code>&lt;nscreen:message</code> xml snipped out of the message as per
	  the extended status information.
	</para>

	<para>
	  (c) has the advantage of predefined capability discovery mechanism
	  (though this could easily be added alongside (b)), the multi-stage
	  processing it facilitates might add extra flexibility making
	  everything bit more future proof, and bulk of the mechanism would be
	  nScreen-agnostic, with the extension being limited to defining the
	  payload. BUT, there seems to be no API in telepathy for this at the
	  moment, so that would require implementing this whole stack (also, how
	  well is xep-0050 supported outside of telepathy, i.e., we are looking
	  for non-telepathy deployment, and excessive work required could slow
	  this down).
	</para>

	<para>
	  So, (c) seems like the ideal solution, the big question is how much
	  effort is needed; I don't think Telepathy currently supports this.
	</para>
	</annotation>
      </section>

      <section xml:id="messaging-commands-format">
	<title>Message Format</title>

	<para>
	  The top level message element is <code>&lt;nscreen:message</code> with
	  the following required attributes:

	  <variablelist>
	    <varlistentry>
	      <term>
		version
	      </term>
	      <listitem>
		<para>
		  The nscreen protocol version,
		</para>
	      </listitem>
	    </varlistentry>

	    <varlistentry>
	      <term>
		type
	      </term>
	      <listitem>
		<para>
		  Tthe message type (see below and <xref
		  linkend="appendix-dtd"/>),
		</para>
	      </listitem>
	    </varlistentry>

	    <varlistentry>
	      <term>
		time
	      </term>
	      <listitem>
		<para>
		  Time of message dispatch, expressed according to ISO 8601,
		  with at least millisecond precision.
	      </para>
	    </listitem>
	    </varlistentry>
	  </variablelist>
	</para>
      </section>

      <section xml:id="messaging-command-types">
	<title>Message types</title>

	<para>
	  The following types of messages are defined:

	  <variablelist>
	    <varlistentry>
	      <term>
		command
	      </term>
	      <listitem>
		<para>
		  A command sent from app A to app B to executed directly by app
		  B; the message payload is held by a
		  <code>&lt;nscreen:command</code> element.
		</para>
	      </listitem>
	    </varlistentry>

	    <varlistentry>
	      <term>
		transfer
	      </term>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
		A request by application A to application B to transfer
		B's activity to application C; the message payload is held by
		<code>&lt;nscreen:transfer</code> element.
	      </para>
	    </listitem>
	    </varlistentry>

	    <varlistentry>
	      <term>
		find
	      </term>
	      <listitem>
		<para>
		  A request by app A to a control app C to identify suitable app
		  B to dispatch a command to. The message payload uses
		  <code>&lt;nscreen:transfer</code> element.  Rationale: because
		  of the need to facilitate e2e encryption, commands cannot be
		  proxied through control applications; the Find request allows
		  clients to initiate a transfer to an application that might
		  not yet be running on the target device (i.e., C will take
		  care of spawning a suitable client if one is not available).
		</para>
	      </listitem>
	    </varlistentry>

	    <varlistentry>
	      <term>
		found
	      </term>
	      <listitem>
		<para>
		  A reply by control application C to application B in response
		  to earlier find request. This is similar to a Transfer
		  request, but is only generated in response to previous Find
		  request; the <code>&lt;transfer</code> element is used for the
		  payload of this reply.
	      </para>
	    </listitem>
	    </varlistentry>
	  </variablelist>
	</para>
      </section>

      <section xml:id="messaging-commands-time">
	<title>Message time</title>

	<para>
	  The message dispatch time must have at least millisecond precision;
	  consequently all nScreen capable devices are required to keep local
	  clock accurate to a degree necessary to generate time stamps with the
	  required accuracy.
	</para>
      </section>

      <section xml:id="messaging-commands-example">
	<title>Command example</title>

	<para>
	  The following xml snippet tells some other application to start
	  playing given video starting 3/4 into the video duration:
	</para>

	<programlisting><![CDATA[
<nscreen:message type='command'
                 version='1.0'
                 time='1970-01-01T00:00:00.000Z'>

  <nscreen:command capability='ns-caps-video'
                   activity='ns-activity-play'
                   uri='some random youtube url'
                   progress='0.75'>
        [Optional command data; binary data base64 encoded]
  </nscreen:command>
</nscreen:message>]]>
	</programlisting>
      </section>

    </section>

    <section xml:id="messaging-metadata">
      <title>Common meta-data classes</title>

      <para>
	The canonical definition is given by the DTD (see Appendix A); the
	following information is extracted from the DTD for convenience.
      </para>


      <section xml:id="messaging-metadata-caps">
	<title>Common capability classes</title>

	<para>
	  <itemizedlist>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
		ns-caps-audio: audio playback capabilities
	      </para>
	    </listitem>

	    <listitem>
	      <para>
		ns-caps-video: video playback capabilities
	      </para>
	    </listitem>

	    <listitem>
	      <para>
		ns-caps-image: image display capabilities
	      </para>
	    </listitem>

	    <listitem>
	      <para>
		ns-caps-html: html rendering capabilities
	      </para>
	    </listitem>

	    <listitem>
	      <para>
		ns-caps-control: control application
	      </para>
	    </listitem>
	  </itemizedlist>
	</para>

	<annotation role='comment'>
	    <info>
	      <authorinitials>tf</authorinitials>
	    </info>
	    <para>
	      More stuff should be added here; open to suggestions.
	    </para>
	  </annotation>

	<para>
	  Custom capabilities can be defined, providing these are suitably
	  name-spaced with a custom prefix; custom capabilities must not use
	  'ns-' prefix.
	</para>
      </section>

      <section xml:id="messaging-metadata-activity">
	<title>Common activity classes</title>

	<para>
	  Absence of the 'activity' attribute, or its empty value imply idle
	  state.

	  <itemizedlist>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
		ns-activity-play: playback
	      </para>
	    </listitem>

	    <listitem>
	      <para>
		ns-activity-pause: paused state
	      </para>
	    </listitem>

	    <listitem>
	      <para>
		ns-activity-ffw: fast forward
	      </para>
	    </listitem>

	    <listitem>
	      <para>
		ns-activity-rwd: rewind
	      </para>
	    </listitem>

	    <listitem>
	      <para>
		ns-activity-volume: volume adjustment
	      </para>
	    </listitem>
	  </itemizedlist>
	</para>

	<annotation role='comment'>
	  <info>
	    <authorinitials>tf</authorinitials>
	  </info>
	  <para>
	  More stuff should be added here, open to suggestions.
	  </para>
	</annotation>

	<para>
	  Custom activities can be defined, providing these are suitably
	  name-spaced with a custom prefix; custom activities must not use 'ns-'
	  prefix.
	</para>
      </section>

      <section xml:id="messaging-metadata-attributes">
	<title>Common attributes</title>

	<para>
	  <itemizedlist>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
		uri: uri a of a resource associated with activity
	      </para>
	    </listitem>

	    <listitem>
	      <para>
		uid: uid identifying resource associated with activity.

		<annotation role='comment'>
		  <info>
		    <authorinitials>tf</authorinitials>
		  </info>
		  <para>
		    The idea is being able to use something like, for example,
		    musicbrainz id to identify the resource, though in practice
		    this might be hard to extend beyond audio
		  </para>
		</annotation>
	      </para>
	    </listitem>

	    <listitem>
	      <para>
		volume: volume level (floating point number from &lt;0,1&gt;)
	      </para>
	    </listitem>

	    <listitem>
	      <para>
		progress: activity progress (floating point number from
		&lt;0,1&gt; this is the preferred way of passing information
		such as stream position.
	      </para>
	    </listitem>

	    <listitem>
	      <para>
		position: activity position (floating point number); NB:
		applications should use the 'progress' attribute whenever
		possible instead of 'position'.
	      </para>
	    </listitem>

	    <listitem>
	      <para>
		description: human readable description, suitable for
		presentation to user
	      </para>
	    </listitem>

	    <listitem>
	      <para>
		jid: jabber id; primarily for use by messages with 'transfer'
		payload
	      </para>
	    </listitem>

	    <listitem>
	      <para>
		speed: speed of activity (floating point number; 1.0 indicates
		'normal' speed)
	      </para>
	    </listitem>
	  </itemizedlist>
	</para>

	<para>
	  Custom attributes can be defined, providing these are suitably
	  name-spaced with a custom prefix; custom attributes must not use 'ns-'
	  prefix.
	</para>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="messaging-data-transfer">
      <title>Data Transfer Protocols</title>

      <para>
	This section defines standard data transfer protocols to be used by
	nScreen clients; this list does not restrict clients to these protocols
	alone, but sets out preferred protocols.
      </para>

      <section xml:id="messaging-data-transfer-files">
	<title>File Transfers</title>

	<para>
	  <itemizedlist>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
		The preferred file transfer protocol is SI File
		Transfer<citation><xref linkend="xep0096"/></citation>; this
		protocol must be supported by all compliant nScreen clients.
	      </para>
	    </listitem>

	    <listitem>
	      <para>
		It is recommended that clients also implement Jingle
		File Transfer<citation><xref linkend="xep0234"/></citation>;
		this protocol is currently in experimental stage, but once it is
		reaches the draft stage, it will be adopted as the default file
		transfer protocol for nScreen clients.


		<annotation role='comment'>
		  <info>
		    <authorinitials>tf</authorinitials>
		  </info>
		  <para>
		    This has relatively limited practical impact on us, the
		    initial deployment will be Telepathy based, which presumably
		    will hide this distinction from us.
		  </para>
		</annotation>
	      </para>
	    </listitem>
	  </itemizedlist>
	</para>

	<annotation role='todo'>
	  <info>
	    <authorinitials>tf</authorinitials>
	  </info>
	  <para>
	    We should recommend protocols for data streaming, and specifically
	    mandate preferred protocols for streaming of video and audio in the
	    manner we mandate the File Transfers. Presumably around
	    Jingle<citation><xref linkend="xep0166"/></citation>.
	  </para>
	</annotation>
      </section>
    </section>
  </section>

  <?hard-pagebreak?>
  <appendix xml:id="appendix-dtd">
    <title>nScreen DTD</title>
    <programlisting>
<!-- The xi:include line must be aligned directly at the end of this comment,
     as any padding will end up in the final document !!! --><xi:include
    parse="text"
    href="./nscreen-protocol.xsd" />
    </programlisting>
  </appendix>

  <bibliography>
    <title>External Resources</title>

    <biblioentry xml:id="rfc3920">
      <bibliomisc>
      <link xlink:href="http://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc3920">RFC 3920</link>
      </bibliomisc>
    </biblioentry>

    <biblioentry xml:id="rfc3923">
      <bibliomisc>
      <link xlink:href="http://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc3923">RFC 3923</link>
      </bibliomisc>
    </biblioentry>

    <biblioentry xml:id="xep0050">
      <bibliomisc>
      <link xlink:href="http://xmpp.org/extensions/xep-0050.html">XEP-0050</link>
      </bibliomisc>
    </biblioentry>

    <biblioentry xml:id="xep0054">
      <bibliomisc>
      <link xlink:href="http://xmpp.org/extensions/xep-0054.html">XEP-0054</link>
      </bibliomisc>
    </biblioentry>

    <biblioentry xml:id="xep0060">
      <bibliomisc>
      <link xlink:href="http://xmpp.org/extensions/xep-0060.html">XEP-0060</link>
      </bibliomisc>
    </biblioentry>

    <biblioentry xml:id="xep0084">
      <bibliomisc>
      <link xlink:href="http://xmpp.org/extensions/xep-0084.html">XEP-0084</link>
      </bibliomisc>
    </biblioentry>

    <biblioentry xml:id="xep0096">
      <bibliomisc>
      <link xlink:href="http://xmpp.org/extensions/xep-0096.html">XEP-0096</link>
      </bibliomisc>
    </biblioentry>

    <biblioentry xml:id="xep0166">
      <bibliomisc>
      <link xlink:href="http://xmpp.org/extensions/xep-0166.html">XEP-0166</link>
      </bibliomisc>
    </biblioentry>

    <biblioentry xml:id="xep0174">
      <bibliomisc>
      <link xlink:href="http://xmpp.org/extensions/xep-0174.html">XEP-0174</link>
      </bibliomisc>
    </biblioentry>

    <biblioentry xml:id="xep0234">
      <bibliomisc>
      <link xlink:href="http://xmpp.org/extensions/xep-0234.html">XEP-0234</link>
      </bibliomisc>
    </biblioentry>

  </bibliography>
</article>
